I'll be introducing
our speaker for today.
So Andrew Lampinen is a member
of technical staff at Anthropic.
And previously, he was a
staff research scientist
at Google DeepMind and received
his PhD in cognitive psychology
here at Stanford.
His research interests
bridge AI and cognitive
science on topics including
learning, generalization,
and representation in language
models, agents, and humans,
as well as broader
issues methodologies
for generalizable research.
And feel free to check
out his Substack for more.
And without further ado,
I'll hand it off to Andrew.
[APPLAUSE]
So I think a question that's
motivated a lot of my work
over the years is the question
of what computational principles
are shared across natural
and artificial intelligence?
And that's a question that I
want to touch on in this talk,
even though this is a
class about transformers
or a seminar series
about transformers.
And in particular, the question
that I want to think about here
is how do language models
generalize from what they learn?
And is there anything from
that could tell us something
about how the systems of
natural intelligence work,
the different ways that
natural intelligences learned?
And this work started
from observing
that there's two different ways
that language models can learn.
This is probably not
surprising to you.
Of course, one way they learn
is that over a large training
corpus, we optimize the
network's parameters in order
to get them to encode some
knowledge or some skills
that we want them to have.
But the other thing,
one of the things
that got people most excited
about language models
in the first place
was their ability
to learn from
information in context.
You can just put some
examples of a task
or some facts or some documents
into the language model's
context, and the models
can use that information
to learn new things, sometimes
even to learn new languages
or do fairly sophisticated
things like that.
And the cool thing about
doing cognitive science
on models like
this is that we can
do all kinds of
controlled experiments
that would be very hard to
do on natural intelligences,
like we can take
novel information.
We can put it into
these different sources,
and we can ask how the
system uses that information
to make predictions in a
response to further questions
or tasks or so on.
And the experiments
I'm going to tell you
about today come
from doing this work.
And in particular,
I'm going to tell you
about a series of works we've
done where we found some pretty
striking differences in
how these models generalize
from the information that's
stored in their parameters
and from information in context.
And then after that, we came to
studying several paths to bridge
this generalization gap.
And at the end, I'll come back
to talk about these bigger
picture questions about
how these findings might
relate to natural intelligence.
And if you're
interested, the things
I'm going to talk
about today come mostly
from this series of three
works on the generalization
of language models from
in-context learning and fine
tuning, latent learning, and
improving latent generalization
using test time compute.
Awesome.
So let's dive in by
talking about learning
in parameters and in context.
So the inspiration
for this work really
started from this nice
paper, The Reversal Curse.
Have you seen this paper
or heard of this paper?
Not too many, OK.
So this was a paper
from Owin Evans' group.
And what they showed is that
if you take a language model
and you fine tune it on
some facts in one order,
like you tell it,
Daphne Barrington
is the director of A
Journey Through Time,
if you then test that
model on a question
like who is Daphne Barrington?
The model will do quite well.
But if you ask it
the question that
forces it to reverse
the relation,
like who is the person who
directed A Journey Through Time,
the model has quite a hard
time answering that question.
So this is what the authors
termed the reversal curse,
that models are tied to the
direction in which they've
learned a relation.
They can't easily reverse it.
But the thing that surprised
us about seeing this work
is that if you try this
experiment in the chat,
for example, the models
are perfectly fine at it.
If you give them
some made up fact,
like Z packs are
bigger than carpools,
then carpools are smaller than Z
packs, this was actually-- well,
this is a reversal.
And in a paper we did earlier
with much simpler language
models, this was our
easy baseline condition
that all the models were
basically at ceiling at.
And so this made us
ask the question is
it possible that the way
that models generalize
from information that they
encounter in their context
is different from how they
generalize from information
they've stored in
their parameters?
And this would be an
interesting finding
because there's actually
a lot of theoretical works
that have argued that
in-context learning is basically
doing some form of
approximate gradient descent,
at least in settings
where gradient descent is
the optimal thing to do.
So the question we asked
in this first paper
was, which generalizes
better, a language model
that's been fine-tuned
on a new data set or one
that's got the whole
data set in its context?
So what we did is we took
various data sets that contain,
let's say, thousands of
documents, hundreds of thousands
of tokens, and we
looked at different ways
that we could teach the language
model about this information.
The first way is that you
just take the data set,
you fine-tune the model
on it in the standard way.
And the second way, now that we
have fairly long context models,
is that you can just
concatenate that whole data set,
give the model
document separators
and put the entire
data set in context.
And then in both
of these settings,
we're going to test how the
model makes generalizations
from the data in this data set.
For example, reversals
of relations but also
more complex kind
of structures like
syllogistic generalizations.
Does that make sense?
Cool.
So I'm first going to
show you some results
on the original
reversal curse data set.
This is us replicating
the findings
from that work on
a different model.
So if you look at the
reversal accuracy,
a pre-trained
model is at chance.
When you fine-tune the model
on the relations in only one
direction, it actually
gets slightly worse
than chance on these reversals.
But if you just put the
entire data set in context,
the model is able to answer the
reversals with 99% accuracy.
So there's a big gap
between the model's ability
to generalize from information
that's fine-tuned on
and its ability to generalize
that kind of information
in context.
We also tested other kinds
of structures in this paper,
for example, syllogistic
generalization.
So syllogisms, you
might from classic logic
are these sets of
two propositions,
like all zamp are snaff,
no snaff are plusk,
that logically imply
a third proposition,
like no zamp are plusk.
We set up these syllogisms
with these nonsense nouns.
So we knew there
were things that
weren't in the training data.
And we just looked at if we
train the models on documents
that contain
information like this,
will they be able to generalize
to the logical implications
of those things?
And here, again, we see,
well, pre-trained models
are at chance because these
are all made up facts.
If we fine-tuned models on
these kinds of documents,
they do get a little bit of
above chance generalization
to the held out tests,
but not very much.
And in-context
learning, where we just
take the entire data set of
thousands of these documents
and put it in
context, is actually
able to generalize better.
So these are two examples of
how in-context learning can
generalize better
than fine-tuning
to certain kinds of tests.
Of course, it's natural
to ask why this is.
And I think the answer
is that there's actually
a lot of structures on--
examples of these
structures on the internet
in the training data.
People reversing a
relation in a document
in an essay in a logical
argument, of course,
is actually a
pretty common thing.
And so it's natural
for the models
to learn how to use these
kinds of structures in context.
But then the question is,
of course, why don't they
learn how to generalize them
appropriately from fine-tuning?
Well, a natural possibility
that occurred to us
was that maybe it is something
about fine-tuning itself.
Maybe the models don't really
learn that much in fine-tuning.
Maybe if we pre-train
them from scratch,
the models would be
able to generalize
these kinds of relations
more appropriately.
So to test that hypothesis, we
took a small language model,
one we could train from scratch,
and we created a large data set
with 20,000 relationships.
With most of them, the
reversals were trained.
But 1% of them were held out.
And the way this
data set looked there
was some prefixed data that
was just filler, basically,
for data diversity.
There's some trained relations
that are like X contain Y,
for example.
And there's also some in-context
learning training sequences,
where you get a forward like W
contains Z, and then a reverse,
Z are the subset of
W. And what we did
is that we held out a
few of the reversals
like Y is a subset
of X and we just
tested how well the models were
able to generalize to these.
And what we find is that if
you test the model's memory
for the trained relations,
even in a new context,
they do very well.
If you test their ability
to take one of the trained
relations for which the
reversal was held out
and reverse it in context,
they also do perfectly at that.
But they still get absolutely 0
generalization to the reversals.
So this is really not just
a phenomenon of fine-tuning.
It's something more fundamental
about how the models generalize
from relational information
in their training data.
And it's not just
about reversals.
We looked at other
kinds of structures
too, like this codebooks data
set, where the model is trained
on information about
how they encode
different kinds of
information in different--
you can think of them
as different languages.
And then we give it
examples of using
some of the encoding
words from each language
but not all of them.
And then we test its ability
to use the other encoding
words that it hadn't
seen used in training.
And again, in this
context, we find
that the models are able to
recall the information well.
If the information
is in-context,
they're able to use it flexibly.
But they're not able to
put those pieces together
in order to generalize
to the held out tests.
Yes, there's a question.
[INAUDIBLE]
When you say no
context, you just
prompted to translate
the unknown thing,
relying on the word
knowledge in the model?
Correct.
Yeah, so basically, an example
of the no context sequences
are like this.
So we say codebook one.
So that tells the model
which codebook it should use.
And then we give it the
sequence to translate
and we test how well it
generalizes to the test.
[INAUDIBLE] like, where
partially it did some
and partially it didn't?
I don't think we have any
examples of that in the paper.
But I think it would basically
get the ones right that it knows
and the ones wrong
that it doesn't.
I should say that we do--
this is not shown on this graph.
But we do have tests where
there's known encodings
but in novel
sequences and stuff.
And it generalizes
well to those.
So it's not just that.
It's totally overfit to
the trained data set.
Yes.
Other questions?
Just a quick question for
the interesting experiment
from the last slide.
So I'm wondering
if you're trying
to also gradually increase
the percentage of data
that is a reversal and see where
do you get to the breakpoint.
So basically is
it enough to just
have 5%, 10% of
examples [INAUDIBLE]?
You mean for the
in-context learning part?
Pre-training, right?
Yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Yeah, we didn't
try exactly that.
I think the answer will depend
on other features of the data
diversity because I
think it's about--
we've seen this in
a lot of other work.
It's about the relative
diversity of where
you see reversal examples.
You have to have a
certain minimal amount
to learn how to do that
structural processing.
But you also need some
amount of diversity
to convince the model
that should generalize
beyond the training examples.
So I don't know exactly
where the cutoff
would be with this though.
It's a good question.
I have one more.
Yes.
Did you always encode these
propositions in English?
Do you try doing it in
a more formal calculus?
Is there any ambiguity?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, great question.
So for these models that are
trained-- so for the experiments
on the pre-trained models, we
always did things in English.
For these experiments where the
models are trained from scratch,
the model doesn't anything about
English or any other language
because we're training
it from scratch.
So it's all tokens.
But you can think
of them as being
basically formal statements.
You could replace this contain
token with a containment
operator from math.
And so you could think of these
as being formal statements.
I don't think it makes
a big difference.
Although, these
reversal things are--
it could be that they are
formatting details that
would make a difference here.
Did you see the same behavior
across different model
architectures or just
different popular--
Yeah, so that's
a great question.
So the short answer
is it depends.
The reversal thing
in particular,
there's been a lot
of work on this,
mostly not by us
but by other people.
And here are some
things that fix it.
Having a bidirectional
transformer fixes it.
That's obvious.
There are also things you can do
that are changing the learning
objective that also fix it.
I'll maybe come back
to this at the end
because it relates to
some of the things I'll
talk about later.
But, yeah, it's definitely
not architecture independent,
but it is a pretty systematic
feature of architectures
that do causal next token
prediction without doing
some trick to avoid it,
I guess I would say.
Awesome.
Cool.
Let me move on.
So this is two examples.
There's more in
the paper showing
that even if you train
a model from scratch,
there's certain
kinds of structures
that the models just
fail to generalize even
when they have enough data
to support them generalizing
in context.
So we're really confident
that they're learning
these structures from the data.
And the way I've been
thinking about this
more recently is that there's
many types of training data
that have explicit information
but also convey something
latently.
So you can think of the
reversals as like this.
There's some
explicit information
which is a forward relation,
like X is Y's parent.
There's some latent information
like who Y's parent was.
The multi-hop
syllogism-like data.
Again, there's multiple explicit
statements, like X is Y's parent
and Y is Z's parent.
And then there's some
latent information
that they imply like Z
is the grandchild of X.
There's other structures
where things like this
have been observed, where
models aren't always
good at generalizing, like
cross-lingual generalization
or this generalization to
alternative goals, which
is something we think
about in the paper.
So I think that when models
are exposed to information that
conveys some underlying
latent information,
they won't always be able to
generalize that information
effectively if they've just been
trained on the explicit bits.
And what I think-- so to
try to sketch this out
in a different way, if you
think of the training documents,
when we do parametric
learning on the model,
when we train information
into its parameters,
it consolidates
information that integrates
across a lot of documents,
but it's a bit more
tied to how that
information was explicitly
conveyed in the documents.
And that means that the model
is less flexible in using
that information at test time.
By contrast, when we do
in-context learning, of course,
you can fit relatively
little information in there,
but it's available in richer
detail in a way that can be more
flexibly used at test time.
Does that distinction
make sense?
OK, awesome.
Yes.
And I do want to
convey, though, that
this consolidated information
is important for the model's
generalization.
It is very much the
parametric information
that's allowing the models to
learn how to use information
more flexibly at test time.
So I'm definitely not saying
that the parametric learning
is unimportant.
And indeed, the way
that I think about this
is that in-context
learning is better
at using specific pieces
of information flexibly.
But parametric
learning is better
at extracting statistical
structures that
are common across many
different documents.
And those include
the structures that
support flexible in-context
learning and the structures that
support other kinds
of generalization.
And if you're
interested in that,
I think you can see some nice
examples in this paper, Deep
Sequence Models Tend to
Memorize Geometrically.
I don't agree with
everything in this paper,
but I think it shows
some nice examples of how
statistical learning
across many documents
can extract a statistical
structure that is actually
harder for models
to use in context.
Cool.
I'll show you one example
because I think this is actually
an important reason that
these failures of latent
generalization are not
so obvious unless you
do controlled experiments.
And the example works like this.
So language models
often generalize better
than 0% in practice.
And this latent
generalization story
would suggest that they're
really missing all the latent
structure in the data.
So, for example,
if we train models
on something like
our syllogism tests
on statements all
birds have wings,
eagles are a type
of bird, and then
test them on the
statement eagles
have wings, that
would probably be
a hard generalization for them
to make from their parameters,
easier in context.
But if as in natural
training data,
the model would get lots of
other examples of words that
tend to co-occur
together, like eagles fly,
and pigeons are a type
of bird, and pigeons
have wings and pigeons fly,
and hawks are a type of bird.
And Hawks have
wings and Hawks fly.
Then suddenly, this test
statement that eagles have wings
might not be so hard.
The models might
be able to infer it
from word co-occurrences alone.
And indeed, this is what we find
in some tests in these papers,
that if you give the model
enough statistical structure,
it can skip the need for
doing systematic reversals
or syllogistic
inferences and just
generalize based on the
word co-occurrences alone.
So this is an example of
how parametric learning can
do types of generalization
that work around its failures
to do more structured
relational generalization.
Does that make sense?
That can go horribly
wrong, right?
Oh, yeah.
Totally.
So--
Meaning this would prove it
would learn nonsense things,
just word co-occurrences?
Correct.
Yeah, so I think the statistics
are useful in expectation.
And so the models
will learn things
that are useful in expectation.
But in any particular
instance, those
can lead to incorrect
generalizations.
But I think this is a general
phenomenon of learning systems,
I might be so bold as to say.
It's also the case
that, in-context,
the models will make mistakes.
It's also the case that when
you teach humans something,
they will make
mistakes about how
to generalize that information.
It's just a really hard
problem to get everything right
all the time.
I'm just wondering, though,
if the word co-occurrences are
boosted by some glimmer of
latent understanding better
than chance.
Or is it--
Well, so I do
really think this is
a legitimate mode
of generalization,
just to be clear.
I think the model should
be integrating information
across these examples
to infer that things
that are birds and fly
typically have wings.
I think that's a
legitimate generalization.
Now, it's interesting because
if you took a slightly different
example, like
penguins fly, where
these co-occurrence
structures would
lead to that generalization,
maybe it's not licensed there.
And you will see that
models get it wrong.
And also young children
actually get these statements
wrong some of the time.
But as we develop more refined
understanding of the world,
we can repair that.
And I think it's very
similar for the models.
This statistical learning
is helpful on average.
It will get certain
kinds of things wrong,
but you just need
more data to fix that.
It's the short answer.
Of course, the models might be
able to do more sophisticated
things in context or using
other information sources
or methods, et cetera.
Does that make sense?
Yes.
Can we think of
this as compression?
When we see a statement
in the forwards direction,
that's useful because I've
seen in the training set.
But the reverse is lost in
compression parametrically.
Yeah, I think you
can think about it
in that way to some extent.
I think it's tricky
because, at some level,
what I want to argue is that--
I think there's a
story which this
supports that compression can
be useful for generalization.
But I think there's also cases
where the compression loses
information that's important
for generalization.
And I think that's what
you're pointing to.
So I think that's just an
important tension to highlight,
that compression is maybe
useful for extracting
certain kinds of
structure and making
it more readily available.
At the same time,
if it's lossy, it
loses information that
might be important
and that could be useful in
some situations to some extent.
Awesome.
Cool.
So the question
we're going to ask
in the next section of the
talk is, well, all right.
So maybe statistical structures
could allow the models
to generalize in some cases.
But are there some
ways that we could
get the models to
generalize, even when there
aren't such statistical cues?
Is there some way
that we can really
get the models to learn
the latent structure
or to generalize it?
Cool.
And I'm going to suggest 2 and
1/2 or three paths to doing
this.
So the first is a train
time offline method,
which is just that we're
going to augment the training
data using in-context learning,
and then distill that back
into the model's
parametric knowledge.
And the second is one
to two online methods,
which is that we're
going to try to retrieve
the information from
memory at test time
to make it into an
in-context task.
And in particular,
we're going to look
at both doing explicit
retrieval from episodic memory
or implicit retrieval
that's learned via RL.
So the first method
is very simple.
It's the dumb first
thing we thought of.
And it's a pretty simple idea.
It's just if in-context
learning generalizes better,
let's see if we can use it to
make those generalizations ahead
of time and cache
them for the future.
So what we did is we took
the data set, the model,
we prompted it with
the data set in context
to generate
reasoning traces that
elaborate upon the documents
that fill in missing reversals
or make links between
documents that aren't
explicit in the data set.
Then we add these new
conclusions back into the data
set and fine-tune on
this whole larger data
set, the original training data
and the augmented reasoning
traces.
So just to make that really
explicit, take the training set.
We concatenate it as context.
We take individual documents one
at a time and we pull them out
and we ask the model things
like make connections
between this document and the
other documents in context.
And then the model
says something like,
oh, I see that in this
document, Dax are a type of fep
and I learned earlier
or in another document
that feps can zarp, and
therefore, Dax can zarp.
Make sense?
Cool.
And what we find is that this
augmented fine-tuning strategy
can generalize, as
well as in-context
learning on reversal-like tasks,
and maybe even better on things
like syllogisms because
it allows the model
more chances to fill
in missing links.
Makes sense?
Cool.
So one way to work around these
latent generalization failures
is using in-context learning to
augment the fine-tuning data.
And that can improve the
model's generalization.
Now, I think there's
been a kind of reaction
against the idea of synthetic
data discovering new knowledge.
And I hate to throw my colleague
Dave Pfau under the bus
because he's a very
smart guy, but I
liked to take this
screenshot from him,
which says I'm absolutely
begging researchers to learn
the data processing inequality.
You can't discover new knowledge
from synthetic data generated
from existing knowledge.
And I think this tweet is not
wrong, but it's misleading.
And the point I want
to make is that what
we're doing when we
augment training data
is not that we're
creating new information.
The information is really
there in the data already.
It's just that we're taking
information that's implicit,
that's latent in
the data, and we're
extracting it out and making
it explicit and easily
accessible to the model.
So, for example, if there's
a statement like all X are Y,
no Y are Z in the
training corpus,
then the statement no X are Z
is already implied by those.
The information is in there.
But it's not explicit.
And when we do the
in-context augmentation,
we're taking the information out
and we're making it explicit.
And if you're interested
in this line of thinking,
I think these are two very
nice and very different
papers on the topic.
One is this paper
by Tania Lombrozo,
Learning by Thinking in
Natural and Artificial Minds,
and this older paper
from here at Stanford
from Stefano Ermon's group, A
Theory of Usable Information
Under Computational Constraints.
OK, so we were excited
about this for a while
and we put out a
preprint on this topic.
But the thing that
bothered us about it
was that it's just
not conceivable
that we could always know
how information would
be useful in the future in
order to augment the data ahead
of time.
And here's an example that I
was thinking about at the time.
Imagine you're reading
a paper or maybe you're
working on your dissertation.
Here's a paper I read was
working on my dissertation.
And it's conceivable that I
could augment my understanding
of the paper by
thinking about how
it could relate to my
dissertation or something.
But it's pretty unlikely that I
would think, oh, in five years,
I'm going to be researching how
language models use information
in context and maybe
something from this paper
will be relevant to my
understanding of that.
I wasn't even really thinking
about language models that much
at the time.
And so the question
is how could we
get models to use
information even
if we didn't know at training
time that it would be useful?
And the answer that
we came up with
was, well, maybe this is
what retrieval is good for.
Maybe if we can just take
knowledge from episodic memory--
this is the
hippocampus, by the way,
which is what does episodic
memory in humans mostly.
We could take the knowledge
from episodic memory.
We could retrieve
it into context.
And then the models
would be able to use
that knowledge more flexibly in
order to answer some question.
I want to highlight that,
for the experiments that I'm
about to show you, we used an
Oracle episodic memory, which
is totally cheating.
And the reason we did that, it
has perfect recall but imperfect
precision.
So it always recalls
something that
is useful for solving the task
but a bunch of other things
that are distractors.
The reason we did that
is just because we didn't
know how to do good retrieval.
And I'll come back to that
at the end of the talk.
So what we find is that if we
use this cheating retrieval
system, if we compare
on a reversal task
the generalizations of
the forward direction,
both parametric learning
and episodic retrieval
do equally well
on generalization.
But when we go to
the reversal test,
again, parametric learning
totally fails the reversals.
But a system that can do
episodic retrieval, even
when it's retrieving
a bunch of distractors
generalizes very well.
And similarly, on the codebooks
task that I showed you earlier,
both the parametric learner and
the system with episodic memory
can do very well on
the training splits.
But on the latent
test condition,
only the system with episodic
memory can generalize well.
So this shows some cases where
episodic retrieval, by bringing
learning experiences
into context,
can allow the system to use
them more flexibly in order
to support flexible
generalization.
Yes.
It's loading the episodes
from the [INAUDIBLE]?
That's correct.
Yeah, so this is just taking
documents from pre-training
and sticking them
back into context.
And that can dramatically
improve the generalization.
So it can still do that X to Z
relationship that's missing just
by pulling out X to Y
and Y to Z. In context,
is that [INAUDIBLE]
asked the question?
Yeah.
Just to be clear, there's
been a long series of work
before we worked on this topic
showing that retrieval augmented
generation is a good
way of getting models
to answer questions about
factual information and stuff.
And the way I think
about this work
is we're basically
showing a mechanism
by which this might be true.
Even for documents
that have been trained
into the parameters, having that
information available in context
can allow the models
to use it more flexibly
and to answer questions better.
Would it be fair to
say you can extract
the true content from
pre-training quite
well, but just not relations?
So it's complicated.
It's that the models can extract
the relations from pre-training
quite well, but they need
to be cued in the right way.
So if you ask them about it
in the forward direction,
you can ask them in a way that's
quite different from training.
As long as you cue it with the
first part of the relation,
the model will do a
decent job of continuing
with the second part.
But it's just that
they don't have
a good way of going backwards,
unless that information is
already in context.
But hold that thought because
it relates to something
we'll come to in a second.
Other questions?
OK, so we totally cheated on the
episodic retrieval part there.
But a natural question you
can ask, as I was alluding to,
is whether the
models could learn
how to do this via
reinforcement learning
without needing to do explicit
retrieval or augmentation.
And the intuition
here is that-- look
at this graph I
showed you earlier.
The models already
know the relations.
They can state them
in a new context.
They already know
if the relation
is in context how to
do the reversal using
in-context learning.
They just need to put
those pieces together
in order to solve the task.
And so what we want to
ask in this paper is,
could the model learn to
regenerate the information
that it needs in its
chain of thought,
thereby bringing that
information back into context
and enabling it to
use it more flexibly?
And in particular, can we
use reinforcement learning
to teach the models to do this?
So the way we tested this is we
took a model, we fine-tuned it
on several data sets
containing new information,
completely non-overlapping
information, even though I copy
pasted these documents here so
it looks like it's overlapping.
And then, of course, we can
test the model's generalization
just after fine-tuning, as
we did in the earlier papers.
But we can also do
reinforcement learning
to teach the model how to
reason on one of these data sets
and then test whether
that allows the model
to learn how to reason
to generalize better
on the other data set.
Does that make sense?
Awesome.
And what we find is
that doing this process,
if we do reinforcement
learning on--
whoops.
Some editing issue here.
If we do reinforcement
learning on one data set,
data set A, it
generalizes to data set--
to reasoning on
data set B. Whereas,
this augmentation bar here is if
you just do augmentation on data
set E--
sorry, data set A, it doesn't
generalize to data set B.
This is showing the
generalization for syllogisms.
You can see the amount
of generalization.
This red bar is the
reasoning generalization.
You can see the amount
of generalization
varies across conditions.
And in particular,
reversals don't
get that much
generalization benefit
from this in-context
recall strategy as opposed
to retrieval which
did very well.
And the reason this
is is that, basically,
in order to solve a
reversal-type problem,
the model has to
recall the information
in the other direction.
And the whole point of
reversal is that that's hard.
It's hard to get from one
direction to the other.
And so the way the
model is able to get
anything above chance
on this is just
going through and enumerating
all the things it's
seen in the data set until it
happens to hit the right one,
and then it can go, oh,
I can reverse that now.
And so the model is able
to do this above chance
on the test set because
the test set only
has thousands of entities.
And so a decent
amount of the time, it
can enumerate hundreds
of them and happen
to hit on the right one.
But obviously, this isn't a very
practical solution at scale.
So this shows a glass
half full story.
Models can learn
via reinforcement
learning how to regenerate
information that they
need in context at test time.
And this can help with some
of the problems quite a lot,
but doesn't necessarily
help with all of them.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
The augmentation.
So this is different because the
augmentations was at train time.
So when you have
the documents there,
then you generate
thinking traces from them.
And that's an easier problem
because the information
is available.
This is the model has to learn
how to pull the information out
that's relevant
to solving a task.
And for something
like syllogisms,
it's able to do
that decently well
because you can follow
the chain of links.
You can be like, oh, let's see.
I know all Dax are--
what do I know about Dax?
So let's see all Dax
are fep or whatever.
And so it can reason
through the chain
to solve those
kinds of problems.
For reversals, it's harder.
But reversals are very easy
with in-context augmentation,
especially because at least
reversals you can anticipate
might be something you would
care about at test time.
Cool.
So I've shown you a
few different paths
to better generalization from
leveraging in-context reasoning.
The first is a train
time or offline path,
where we augment the
training data in context
and then distill those
augmented data into the model's
parametric knowledge.
And the second are some
online test time paths
where we either
explicitly retrieve memory
or we train the model via IRL to
implicitly retrieve information
from the training corpus.
And either way, having
that information available
back in context makes the models
better at answering these test
questions.
Yes.
What's the difference
between the models
being able to do this,
generate this augmented data,
and then also do
[INAUDIBLE] regeneration
and just doing it [INAUDIBLE]?
So it's basically--
well, actually,
let me go to the next slide.
And maybe this
will make it clear.
And if not, we can
come back to it.
So basically, these methods
have different trade-offs.
So first of all, let's just
talk about the performance.
Doing train time augmentation.
If you know what
questions you're
going to care
about at test time,
this can achieve performance
as good or better
than in-context learning.
If we do test time
episodic retrieval,
this can also achieve
good performance.
And this RL-based method
achieves good performance
on many kinds of structures,
but not all of them.
So the differences
between these methods
are really about
what they cost when.
And so for the train
time augmentation method,
you have to spend a lot of
extra compute at training time.
You take a bunch of
long context inferences
where you take a
data set and then
you generate further
information from it.
So that's relatively expensive
compute-wise at training time.
But it's relatively
easy for the model
because it has the
information available
and it just has to
generate other inferences
it can make from it.
And it's efficient at test
time because at test time,
we don't do anything
different than if we just
fine tune the model normally.
So it's expensive at
training, free at test.
Doing test time
retrieval, well, it's
free at training
time, which is nice,
but it requires a bunch of extra
inference compute at test time
because now we're making
the test context longer
by prepending a bunch
of documents to them.
That's more expensive.
And I didn't give
you an answer for how
to do retrieval while
in a general way.
So this isn't even
really a solution.
It's just a gesture at
where a solution might be.
This RL method, it
generalizes beyond things
that we anticipated
ahead of time
we would need to
augment for along
with this one, which is nice.
But it requires extra
inference compute
at training time when you're
doing the reinforcement learning
step and at test time, when the
model has to generate a longer
thinking trace in order
to pull things back out
of its knowledge.
And so, I would say, to
come back to your question,
this one is, in
some sense-- well,
these two are in some
sense easier for the model
because the information gets
into its context somehow.
And all it does is have to
use it in the right way.
Test time retrieval is
maybe the easiest of all
because it knows what question
it's going to use it for.
Train time augmentation
is the model
has to fill in what are the
ways this information might
be useful in the future?
Test time thinking
is hard for the model
because although it knows what
question it's trying to answer,
it doesn't necessarily
know which information
might be useful for that.
And so at least for
things like reversals,
it might have to go through
a lot of information
to try to pull out something
that would be useful.
Make sense?
Awesome.
Cool.
So in the last 10 minutes or so
of the talk, what I want to do
is talk a bit about
the bigger picture
of why I've been
interested in these things
and how it might
relate to some findings
in natural intelligence.
So what I told you at
the beginning of the talk
is that training data
often latently convey more
than their explicit content.
And when you train a
language model's parameters
on these data, what it learns
might be overly tied to what
was explicitly conveyed there.
And so the question that I got
interested in while we were
working on this
is is it possible
that natural intelligence faces
some of these same challenges,
like the parametric
learning that we do
might be more tied
to the explicit way
that we've learned
some information.
And if so, there
might be evidence
that natural
intelligence also uses
these different
kinds of strategies
to bridge the
generalization gap,
doing things like augmenting
or training experiences offline
and retrieving relevant
information online.
And it turns out
that if you look
at the literature
on the relationship
between the
hippocampus, which does
episodic memory in
the brain, roughly,
and the rest of neocortex, which
does more parametric learning,
roughly, you'll find that
the relationship between them
is pretty complicated.
As this paper says, it's not a
simple function of experience
with the hippocampus replays.
And you can find evidence
that the hippocampus
is doing things that look
like offline augmentation.
It's doing preemptive
replay of future problems
that might come up or
that it is reorganizing
our experiences in ways that
might support generalization.
And you can find some evidence
that online replay is helping
us to solve
problems, or at least
could be helping us
to solve problems.
And so it's possible
that natural intelligence
takes a let's throw
everything at the wall
and see what sticks approach
to solving these latent
generalization problems by using
both offline and online methods.
And this, if you're interested
in the neuroscience of it,
could provide a
interesting and different,
I think, from other
perspectives perspective
on why cortical and hippocampal
learning are complementary,
where, again, the parametric
learning is able to integrate
information, statistical
structures, for example,
across many experiences.
But episodic memory, by
preserving specific experiences
in richer detail,
makes them more
available for
flexible reuse later
to solve different
kinds of problems.
Cool.
So coming back to
the big picture
question I posed at the
beginning of the talk, what
computational ingredients are
needed for generalization?
Well, what I want to
suggest is that we
need both consolidated
information, like cache
statistics, facts, and insights
within or across experiences,
procedures for reasoning about
information flexibly in context,
and we need episodic memory
that preserves experiences
in rich detail, allowing access
to information that we didn't
realize would be
important later.
And you can think
of these things
as being some of the functions
of parameters in the language
models on the one
hand and the things
that we put in context for them
on the other hand, at least
with methods like retrieval
augmented generation.
Cool.
So that's it for what
I wanted to say today.
I told you that training
experiences contain
both explicit content and
they convey latent information
that might be useful later.
Language models might not
reason over this effectively
from parametric learning.
But they can use it
flexibly in context.
We showed a variety
of approaches
to bridging this gap, offline
approaches using augmentation
and online using various
forms of retrieval.
And I've suggested
that these might
relate to some findings about
offline and online hippocampal
replay.
Of course, there
might be other things
that the brain is doing
that's smarter than what
we're doing right now.
With that, I would like to
thank all my collaborators,
so especially Arslan,
Sridhar, and Stephanie,
who co-led various parts
of this work, Martin,
who played a big role
in one of the projects,
as well as Effie, Cody, Jorg,
Alex, Diane, Razvan, and Jay.
And thank you all for listening
and thanks to DeepMind
for supporting this work.
If you want more
of my hot takes,
you can follow me
on these platforms.
[APPLAUSE]
And I'm happy to take more
questions/discussion now.
Awesome.
Thanks, Andrew, for the very
insightful and amazing talk.
We'll be soliciting
more questions
now both online and in-person.
So for the folks here, feel
free to raise your hand.
And I'll walk
around with the mic.
Thanks for a good talk.
I was wondering, do you have any
ablation study or sensitivity
activity towards contact size
and billions of parameters
and also sparsity?
And how do they impact or
influence your results?
Yeah, great question.
So for context size, we
do have some experiments
that bear on this.
So I guess the short answer is
that it's quite model dependent.
But I can tell you that for
the models that we used,
they're pretty good at--
if you give them just one piece
of information in context,
they will always get it right.
If you give them hundreds of
thousands of tokens in context,
they'll get it a decent
amount of the time.
It depends on the problem.
But it also depends a lot
on what the information is.
And so there's actually one
of the ablations in our paper.
We look at the reversal
[? course ?] data set,
and we just change
every word in there
to nonsense instead of
the original things,
which are plausible statements
about this person directed
this movie.
And what we find
is that the model's
ability with the same data
set in context, but just
with the names, for example,
replaced with nonsense words,
the model's ability to answer
those questions goes down a lot.
Now, that might be partly a
context length changing confound
because the tokenization
for the names
is shorter than tokenization
for the nonsense words.
But I think it's too big an
effect to be explained by that.
And it's really that retrieval
is context-sensitive.
The model's ability to pull
information out of context
depends on how well it's
learned in pre-training
to pull information of
that type out of context.
And it's just better at
doing that for information
about real entities,
which comes up
all the time in pre-training
than for information
about nonsense words.
So the answer is that
the models are definitely
sensitive to the context
length and that sensitivity
depends on the information that
you're asking them to retrieve.
There was a-- oh, you
asked about sparsity too.
Parameters and [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, parameters.
So I would say, short
answer on parameters
is that larger models are
better at this like most things.
Sparsity, you mean mixture of
experts versus dense models?
I don't have any experiments
that directly address that.
So I can't answer.
I wouldn't expect it to
make that much difference
because, usually, the
sparsity of the model
is in the MLP layers,
not in the attention.
It's really the attention
that's modulating
these in-context effects.
But it could.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Another thing is that you train
to learn new things easier.
But there's a tension in that.
I was just wondering what
assumption of sparsity
that you used.
I see.
Yeah, so most of the
experiments I told you about,
at least the small
model experiments
were done with dense models.
Yeah, it would be interesting
to compare the sparse case.
[INAUDIBLE] in which
closely related to RL
but it's not really real RL?
I find that sometimes when
you're having these models,
you work on doing feedback,
and the application [INAUDIBLE]
feedback is not
really demoralizing
in the sense coming to update
the weights while you're
learning.
And so [INAUDIBLE]
update that in real-time.
So, of course, I was trying
to do something like that.
But it's not
real-time real-time.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so I guess there's
several questions there.
In general, there's
a problem of-- so I'm
going to step back and
give a very big picture
answer to this question.
One of the things
that people thought
about why hippocampal and
cortical learning in humans
were complementary
originally, which
I think is still a very
important part of why they're
complementary, is
that it's important
for the parametric
learning system
to learn slowly because
that allows it to integrate
information across
a lot of experiences
without having interference.
And that's what helps the system
to do statistical generalization
that is useful.
On the other hand, you want to
be able to-- if you're out there
in the world and you almost get
in a car accident or something,
you want to be able to learn
from that one experience and not
have to see it 50,000 times
in order for the statistics
to finally catch up.
And so episodic memory stores
the experiences very rapidly
from a single experience.
And then by replaying
it over time,
it can integrate that
with your other knowledge
and your other
experiences in a way that
preserves the nice slow
learning properties of cortex
but gives you the benefits
of fast generalization.
So indeed, with
that analogy, you
might think that if you just try
to train the model's parameters
from one experience, if you
make a large enough update
to the model's parameters
in order to get it to really
effectively incorporate that
experience in a way that
generalizes to other
instances, you might actually
damage some of the model's
other knowledge in the process.
And so what you
need to do is maybe
some way of storing it
explicitly and either retrieving
that when you need
it or replaying it
on the model to get it to learn
that information over time.
I think people do things
like this to some extent.
I suspect that the issues
with model generalization
are more about the models
being too context-sensitive
in some sense in
what they learn.
The models are very good at
distinguishing different kinds
of situations.
And because of
that, they're very
good at not generalizing
as far as you want them
to in certain kinds of ways.
The model gets some
human feedback.
I don't like this response.
And it's like, OK.
When someone asked
me this question,
I won't give this response.
But if you ask a very
similar question,
it might not have
generalized to that.
So that's my intuition
about what's going on there.
But definitely, I think doing
retrieval of relevant examples
could help with some of
these kinds of problems.
It might cause other
issues, though,
depending on what
kind of generalization
you were looking for.
Hopefully that answered it.
What do you think of the
fact that the model gets
smaller or gets [INAUDIBLE]?
Maybe it will contribute to
this with generic learning
after, let's say, after a month.
You can have this network where
they say, hey, I love this.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, I think there's
lots of interesting things
to be explored in that space.
Yeah, a question
about the slide.
You compared the pros and
cons of the three approaches.
Yes.
Training-data
augmentation, ICL, and RL.
Yeah.
Training data
augmentation was written
that it achieves as good or
better performance than ICL.
So I wonder in which cases it's
achieving better performance?
Yeah, so the basic situation
in which that happens is that--
so think about it this way.
In the in-context learning
case, the model basically
gets one thinking chain's
worth to try to hit
the answer to the question.
In the case that we did the
in-context augmentation,
we actually have
a lot of documents
that we ask the
model to generate
thinking traces from with
the information in context.
And so it's basically
it gets a higher number
of reasoning traces sampled
that could hit on the answer
to the question.
And so, for example,
on the syllogism tasks,
we find that the
models generalize or do
better on the syllogistic tests
with the augmented fine-tuning
than they do from the
in-context learning.
And that's my
explanation for it,
is that you're
getting the model to
by generating more reasoning
traces, its more likely to chain
together the right statements
to make some inference it
needs to make.
Professor [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, but, I mean, well,
I guess, in general,
any question you want to ask
the model that you don't provide
the information in
context at test time,
that information has to come
from reasoning about things
from the training corpus.
Otherwise, there's no way the
model could figure it out.
I have a quick question.
Sure.
OK.
The first one is, if I
understood correctly,
in pre-training, you
have two facts, like fish
lay eggs and chicken lay eggs.
Yeah.
And the inference time
you go fish and chicken
are like each other
in that point.
It will never see the eggs.
I think it--
That may be a bold statement,
but it doesn't generalize.
I think it would actually
probably generalize
that because it's
more of a forward--
at least if it
saw some examples.
[INAUDIBLE]
But let's say you have two
statements like that which
didn't sound so rhythmic,
like they sound same,
you use different words
for X, but it would never
actually fill in that-- it's
unlikely to fill in that gap
basically.
Yeah, so I think
it depends a lot
on the statistics of
the training corpus,
just to be clear.
I showed the example of
the word co-occurrences
can support this in certain
kinds of situations.
But assuming-- there are at
least some situations in which I
agree it won't generalize that.
So my next question,
then, is in [INAUDIBLE]--
and maybe you thought of this.
Maybe you haven't.
You could train the model on
completely abstract sequences,
and it would get all the
generalization capability
it could ever get
in the parameters.
Yeah.
So you have a copyright
free pre-training corpus
that's made up of nonsense
words, where maybe
the tokens will match up then.
But, yeah.
Yeah, so what I want
to say about that is
I think there is some
mileage to be gained
from doing things like this.
And there's various papers
that have shown that you can,
for example, pre-trained
models on formal languages
and you can get some
improvements in how
they learn on real language.
The problem is that,
as I said in the answer
to some of the
earlier questions,
I actually think the statistical
structure is a very good thing
to be learning.
And so, for example, in some
of the earlier work we've done,
we've looked at content
effects on reasoning.
So how language models reason
about logical structures
is very dependent on the
information and the structures
they're reasoning about.
Turns out that that's
true of humans too
and it's true of humans
and language models
in the same ways across
some classic problems that
have been studied in humans.
And the way I think
about it and the way
we wrote about it in that paper
is that the reason for this
is actually that it's like
normatively a good thing, if you
want to make accurate
inferences in the world,
to use all the information
that you can in
order to make those inferences.
And so logical
reasoning is hard to do
and integrating a
bunch of statistics
is relatively easy and natural
for a parametric learner to do,
it makes sense for the system to
not always rely purely on logic,
but to actually use that
statistical structure.
And that will actually help it
to generalize in expectation.
And so I think that if you try
to make a system that's just not
using the statistics
but just generalizing
on the basis of structure
alone, for the same reason
that [? guffi ?] just
wasn't a tractable approach
to AI in real-world
problems where you just have
too many things you could
possibly make inferences about,
you need that
statistical structure
to constrain the
kinds of inferences
that you want the
system to make.
That's what allows the
system to efficiently get
to a feasible answer.
And I think that's important for
both understanding why humans
reason in the quirky and weird
ways that we do sometimes
and for understanding
what language models need.
So I think that you would
need the models to pick up
that statistical
structure at some point.
Yes.
My question is related to that.
But firstly, thank
you for your talk.
Secondly, at the end,
you made a comparison
between the hippocampus and
neocortex and then in-context
learning and
parametric learning.
My first question then
is what do you think is,
from what you've seen,
the coolest similarity
between human brains and natural
learning and machine learning?
And then secondly, where exactly
do you think this metaphor
breaks down?
Yeah, OK.
Great question.
So I think I'm going
to say that there's
been a lot of interesting
work comparing language model
transformer-style attention to
hippocampal memory, not just
our work.
Although, this takes a
different perspective on it.
And James Whittington,
for example,
has done a bunch of
work in this space.
And I think that analogy
is very interesting
because at some
level, you wouldn't
think at all that
transformer-style attention is
doing anything
like what we think
of the hippocampus is doing.
But it is like
pulling information
out from a long
sequence of past states
according to some of weighted
similarity-based lookup.
And when you phrase it in that
way, it's like some things
that people have thought about
the hippocampus as doing.
And James Whittington,
who I mentioned,
has worked on this
analogy quite a bit.
So I think that is an
interesting example of how
you can have systems that are
clearly at the implementation
level completely different.
Whatever the
hippocampus is doing,
it's definitely not doing
transformer-style query value
attention.
But that turned out to have some
similar computational properties
in some ways that can make one
system a good model for another.
So I think that's just
cool as a, I don't know,
example of the separation
of computational and
implementational levels in doing
cognitive science, for example.
Yeah, maybe I'll go
with that as the answer
to your first question.
Where the analogy breaks down.
Well, I already said the
implementation is obviously
the place that breaks down.
But the other place that I think
it breaks down more is that--
let's imagine that you had a--
well, yeah, it's complicated.
But, I mean,
basically, you can't
fit a whole lifetime
of experience
into a language model's context.
That's not tractable.
And yet, the hippocampus
in combination
with the cortex,
because it turns out
there's actually quite
complicated interactions,
and the hippocampus isn't
really storing episodic memories
for your whole life, certainly
not independently anyway,
but the hippocampus is able to
preserve a much larger array
of information.
One of probably consequences
of that, I think,
is that the hippocampus is much
more likely-- at least compared
to the scale of
information we're
putting in the transformers
now, the hippocampus
does much more
generative retrieval.
Most of the-- you
may have seen some
of these stats that
many things you remember
as episodic memories
didn't actually happen,
a non-trivial percentage of
them didn't actually happen.
And you've just
constructed that memory.
And then each time
you think about it,
it becomes a stronger
encoding of that memory.
So there's a lot
of confabulation
of the hippocampus.
That does happen with
in-context learning too.
But I think on the
scales that we have,
it's maybe a lower rate actually
than it is for the hippocampus.
But the flip side
of that is that I
think that perhaps
the generative nature
of the hippocampus is
more flexible in some ways
than transformer
attention is or is
able to do some more
sophisticated kinds
of generalization.
And so those are a few different
ways that the analogy breaks
down, I think.
Maybe I'll go to you since--
Hi.
I'm building a behavioral
constitution for AI,
which [INAUDIBLE]
system prompts.
I was wondering, for
behavioral reliability,
do you think context will
ever match the [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, it's a good question.
I think it depends
on what you mean.
Because I think
usually when people
think about a
constitution, for example,
shaping a model's
behavior, it's like you
want this model when it's
placed in any new situation
to behave in accordance
with the constitution.
And the kinds of
experiments I showed
you are things
where the model gets
a bunch of consistent
information in context
and then it's able to
use that effectively.
I think the models have
a much harder time when
they have inconsistent
information in context.
For example, if you
have a constitution that
says one thing and then you
have a user that's demanding you
to do another thing,
no, my grandma is dying
and I really need you to
hack into this computer
so you can help me to help
her, it's harder for the models
to reconcile those different
sources of information.
And I think because of
that, I think this is--
I'm not necessarily
saying that in-context
will be better or worse than
parametric learning there.
I think that in either case,
it can be hard for the model
to reconcile those different
sorts of information,
like the things that it learned
as parameters, the things that
are in context, and the things
that the user is telling it
right now.
And because of that, it's
hard to guarantee reliability
of either of these
methods, I think.
In some sense,
because the models
are such good
in-context learners,
it's very hard to stop them from
adapting to some weird context
the user gets them.
Yes.
So I think this stuff
is really interesting.
[INAUDIBLE] how much you should
invest in training [INAUDIBLE]
parameter?
And how much of it can
be offset or assisted
by actually
in-contrast learning?
Do you know [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, that's a good question.
I haven't published
anything on those topics.
But there's been some
work, for example--
this is a slightly,
OK, this is slightly
a tangent to your question.
But I'll just read it as an
example of the kinds of things
in this space.
There is for a while
this notion of chinchilla
optimal language
model scaling, which
was about for a given fixed
training budget, how much
should you train your model to
get an optimally good model out
at the end?
And then people realized
later that if you're
going to do a bunch of inference
on your model at test time,
well, you don't just care
about the training compute.
You also care about how good
the model is at test time
relative to its compute.
And that changes the
scaling laws you should fit
for how big of a model you
should train for a given
amount of training compute.
And so similarly,
I think there are
scaling laws you
can fit that trade
off these various
parameters, like how much do
you want to augment your data?
How much do you want
to get new data?
How much do you want to do
compute at training time
versus at test time?
And that will depend
a lot on what exactly
you're trying to get
the system to do.
At what cost?
At what time?
So I'm not sure if I've seen
a paper that explicitly tries
to trade those things off.
But I'm quite confident
that some people out there
are thinking about those issues,
at least at one of the labs,
if not all of them.
Yes.
So you talked about offline
augmenting the training data.
Did you look into
lifting yourself
up from your own bootstraps
or making the model better
without much information?
Yeah, you probe what the
trade offs are of doing that.
What does it get
worse in, if anything.
Yeah, so I think--
OK, I'll say a few
things about this.
So one trade off is
just the inference cost.
And you should actually think
that that's non-trivial.
It's a lot more expensive to
do this offline augmentation
than just to do a fine-tuning
pass over a small data set.
I don't know exactly
the trade off,
but I would guess at least
10 times as expensive
because you have to do a bunch
of inference/generation passes,
then you have to do a training
pass over a larger data set.
And so it's a lot
more expensive.
And that's one of
the major trade offs.
I think that you will
get some hallucination
in the augmented data.
And in our examples, this
was at a low enough rate
that it still worth it to
keep augmenting the data
because, well, I mean,
one way of looking at it
is that if you
get hallucinations
some percent of the time and
you get the right answers
more percent of the time, well,
as long as the hallucinations
are independent from
each other, then
the model will on average
learn the right answer.
I think that's one of the
factors that goes into it.
I think when you do fine-tuning
on a larger data set,
if you don't change
anything else,
you will probably distort
the model's knowledge
of other things more.
And so that's a factor that you
definitely have to consider.
Most fine-tuning methods,
including the ones we used here,
have some kind of
regularization to try
to prevent the model
from drifting too
far from the original model.
And that will tend
to counteract that.
But how exactly those trade
offs depend on how exactly
you're doing the regularization
and stuff like that.
A follow-up.
Did you feel very
satisfied with your choice
of prompt for each generation
of the augmented training data?
Is you want to maybe have
some foreknowledge of the task
you're trying to improve
its performance on.
Yeah.
So you're cheating a little bit.
You're cheating to the
point where you literally
told it the answers.
You have to choose something
in between those points.
Is it satisfying to understand?
Yeah, so we did use
the same prompts
across the different
experiments.
We did ablation on the prompts,
and it actually mattered less
than we thought it would.
But I think if you were--
the experiments in that paper
were all about factual knowledge
of some kind, whether it's
reversals, or syllogisms,
or things like that.
I think if you were like,
now I want to test this out
on a math reasoning
data set, you
might find that those
prompts don't actually
work that well there.
And so I think it's an
important general question how
much the prompts--
how to write prompts that are
sufficiently general that they
could cover anything or how
to adapt prompts to the data
that you're augmenting.
Is there a prompt
you could tell us
that you used for this
reversal reasoning syllogism.
Yeah, so the prompts
that-- you can see them
in the appendix of the paper.
Been a couple of years.
So I don't remember
exactly what they are.
But they are of the character
here's a bunch of documents.
Now here's a
particular document.
Can you rewrite this document
and write any connections
that you can make between
this document and other ones
in the corpus, including
rephrasing things and thinking
about relations between
different entities and so on?
Something like that.
And there's been other methods
like Tatsu's group here
has done some things
along these lines
and various other groups have.
So you can see an
array of prompts
across the literature
on how to do this.
But I think they're all--
our prompts are quite
tied to the factual
and entities setting.
And doing this in a fully
general way is a hard problem.
You were very indirect.
Yeah, I mean, we tried not to--
[INAUDIBLE] much on
logical reasoning.
Yeah, I mean, we
wanted the reviewers
to not feel like we were
totally cheating on that.
But it's hard to
do it perfectly.
Unfortunately, that's all
the time we have for today.
But thanks, everyone, for
your insightful questions.
And let's give another
round of applause
to our speaker for today.
Thank you all for coming.
[APPLAUSE]